Guide to the William Lyon Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Lyon papers.
1745-1926
1791-1833
GEN MSS 79
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
The papers contain correspondence and personal papers documenting the family life, business activities, and travels of William Lyon. Also included is a twentieth-century biographical sketch of Lyon.
Lyon, William, -1748
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were purchased in 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The William Lyon Papers consist of fifteen folders of correspondence and personal papers relating to the life and career of William Lyon (1748-1830). A New Haven native, Lyon was a merchant with Atwater and Lyon until 1795, when he became Cashier of the newly organized New Haven Savings Bank. He was also one of the founders of the Second Company of the Governor's Foot Guards. The papers were purchased in 1987 on the Cecil J. Harribine Fund.
There are two folders of letters in the collection, mostly by Lyon himself. Several date from his 1795 trip to Litchfield as Agent of the Lottery for the Encouragement of Manufacturing and discuss his travels, lottery business, and family news. Letters to his children contain advice and topical comments; for example, in March 1818 he noted that "Republicanism is triumphant throughout the state. Even in New Haven it is not so infamous to be a friend to the rights of man as it once was." There are also single letters by his wife, Lois Mansfield Lyon; his daughter Sarah Lyon Law; and Jared Mansfield, whose 1799 letter from Philadelphia discusses the possibility of war with France.
The personal papers fill thirteen folders, and include Lyon's militia commissions; a proposal for the unification of area churches; the minutes of the Lottery Commission for 1794-75; two circular letters from the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, with two brief drafts of papers on the shape of the earth and decimal currency; and pieces of Lyon's membership certificate in the Philadelphia Anti-Slavery Society. A typescript of Lyon's journal for May-July 1823 is located in folder 8. This is a detailed record of his travels through upstate New York and Canada, and Lyon comments on such topics as the visible wreckage from the Battle of Plattsburgh; his impressions of Irish immigrants in Canada; his surprise at the courtesy of the British officers he encountered; and the damage to a Montreal house looted during a charivari, which he thought "appeared pretty much as my own house had in 1779 after the British visit." The collection also contains his eldest son's Yale diploma, several grocery accounts, and a biographical sketch of Lyon written in 1926.
Lotteries -- Connecticut; Canada -- Description and travel; Connecticut -- History -- 1775-1865; New Haven (Conn.); Lyon, William, -1748; Lyons family
- Box and Folder List, 1791-1833, n.d.
  - Correspondence, 1791-1833, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Accounts, 1802-21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical sketch, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1800-02, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Diploma of William Lyon, Jr., 1810 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - First Society in New Haven, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Journal 1823 May-July: typescript, [1926] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal records, 1745-92, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lottery for the Encouragement of Manufacturing, 1794-95 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Militia commissions, 1783-94 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Militia papers, 1777-93, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1792-1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, 1764-70 (Box 1, Folder 15)